Stop!
站住
Halt!
别跑
Hurry!
快
Stop!
站住
You stop!
别跑 站住
Halt!
别跑
Mr. Feng.
冯哥
Why is he here?
这小子怎么在这儿啊
What's going on over there?
那边什么情况
Just now, a man came to
刚才记者那儿
the place we arrest the journalist
来了一个人
and kidnapped him.
把他劫走了
Who did it?
谁干的
That guy made a mess
那家伙把那儿
over there,
搅得一团糟
so we didn't see who it was.
没看清是谁
Mr. Feng,
冯哥
no one is there.
那边没人
Mr. Feng, how about letting me go in and get...
冯哥 要不我进去把这
Buzz off!
滚
Hello, Sir. How many?
先生您好 一位吗
Mrs. Peng.
彭太太
Come in quickly.
快进来吧
How's the journey?
一路上还顺利吗
Smooth.
顺利
And you?
你呢
Did Feng Guangyun jerk you around?
冯广云没对你怎么样吧
No.
没有
Where is Journalist Peng?
彭记者呢
In the room.
在里面
Hasn't regained his consciousness,
一直昏迷到现在
not yet recovered.
还没醒呢
When I saved him,
我救他的时候
he's already been in a coma
他就已经昏迷了
with wounds all over his body.
身上没一处好的
Feng Guangyun's subordinates
冯广云的人
tortured him severely
对他用了重刑
and repeatedly.
而且不止一次
During this period,
这段时间
they tortured him again and again.
反反复复地在用刑
It's hard to imagine
难以想象
how he managed to hold on.
他是怎么坚持下来的
Can we take him to the hospital?
能送医院吗
No, we can't.
去不了
The police will know as soon as we go there.
去了警察马上就会知道
As for the treatment,
治疗的事情
you don't need to worry.
你就不用担心了
Journalist Peng is a member of the NSO.
彭记者是救国会的委员
We have arranged
已经安排了
to send him
马上就会把他送到
to the clinic of the NSO.
救国会的诊所
Now, I just hope
现在只希望
Journalist Peng can recover as soon as possible.
彭记者能尽快醒过来
Thank you so much.
真是谢谢你们了
The NSO has also
救国会还给我们
arranged a friend
安排了一个朋友
to take care of us
照顾我们
and bring us some food and materials,
给我们送了些吃的用的
so that I don't have to go out.
这样我也不用出去了
Is that person reliable?
人可靠吗
Yes,
可靠
she helped me get through,
这段时间全靠她了
and she's kind to me.
人也挺好的
Don't worry.
放心吧
Once Peng regains consciousness,
等彭记者醒了
we could know
就能知道
what happened
这一段时间
during this time period.
到底发生了什么事
Captain,
队长
does that mean we can conclude
彭记者这个案子
the case of Mr. Peng?
就算结束了吗
I don't know what could happen
往后我不知道
in the future,
会发生什么
but at least the missing case of Journalist Peng
但至少彭记者失踪案
is over.
算是结束了
Can we wait for
那我们三人小组
Journalist Peng to wake up
能不能等
before
彭记者醒过来之后
disbanding our group of three?
再解散
I made an appointment
我和向远生
with Xiang Yuansheng before.
之前就约好了
Our cooperation ends
我们的合作
as soon as we find Peng.
就到找到彭记者为止
Peng is still unconscious.
彭记者还没醒
I've not gotten even a word
我想要的答案
of the answer I want.
还一个字都不知道
Our cooperation cannot end here.
这还不能算合作结束
OK,
好
let's wait until Peng wakes up.
那就到彭记者醒
Agree.
我同意
Mr. Luo.
骆先生
Minmin,
珉敏
everyone has arrived home except you.
家里就等你回家了
Thank you for seeing me home.
谢谢你送我回来
I'm going back now.
我先回去了
Mr. Xiang...
向警官
It's time to go home.
赶紧回去吧
There is soup on the stove.
炉子上熬了汤
You each drink a bowl before going to bed.
一个人喝一碗再睡
Mr. Hua,
华先生
I really appreciate
今天
your help.
谢谢你了
But the next time
以后珉敏
Minmin comes back late,
要是晚回来
her brother and I will take her home.
我和她哥去接她
I don't want to bother you.
不麻烦你了
It doesn't matter,
没关系的
and I'm just on the way.
我这 正好也顺路
Now public order is not very good,
现在治安不好
so you hurry home.
我就不留你了
You two,
你们两个
back to your rooms.
先回屋
When did he come back?
他什么时候回来的
A few days
回来
ago.
有几天了
I found you ask a leave
我看你请了假
but didn't return to the shop to help,
也没有回铺子帮忙
so I guessed that.
就猜到了
Minmin,
珉敏
you didn't get the letter.
你没有收到信
It doesn't matter
其实他为什么不写信
why he didn't write,
不重要
even if he did,
哪怕就算他写了
it also doesn't matter.
也不重要
What matters is that
重要的是
you cannot get his letter.
你收不到他的信
Understand?
你明白我的意思吗
This will be a main problem
这会是
for both of you.
放在你们俩面前的难题
He always disappears
这个人
from your life
总是这样那样的原因
for one reason or another,
在你的生活中消失
without any message.
一点儿消息都没有
It's unfair for you.
太辛苦了
How long is he staying
他这次来上海
in Shanghai this time?
待多久
A week,
一周
a week to fulfill the mission,
一周执行完任务
and then he'll go back.
他就回去了
Minmin,
珉敏
since you will lose contact with him,
既然断了联系
don't rekindle the flame.
就别再回头了
Why are you here?
你干什么
No matter what
不管刚刚
dad just told you,
爸跟你说了什么
I support your decision.
我都支持你的决定
I shouldn't have
我就不应该
kept the journalist alive.
留着那个记者
When he refused to tell me
当初他不肯
where the negatives are,
说出底片在哪儿的时候
I should have asked Zhou Chang
我就应该让周昌
to kill him.
把他给解决了
Sir,
副局长
I can now confirm that
我现在可以确定
Hua Zhen's cohorts are a man and a woman.
华桢的同伙有一男一女
In the hospital of the Shipyard,
在造船所医院
the woman accompanied the journalist's wife.
陪着记者的是个女的
And the man
救出记者出去的
rescued the journalist.
是个男的
But when my men
但是我的人
chased out,
追出去的时候
they viewed only the sight of their back,
只看见背影
and failed to view their faces.
没看清楚他们的样子
I've hired Zhou Chang for so long,
我养了周昌那么长时间
but he didn't even
他连这点儿警惕性
have the slightest vigilance,
都没有
taking so many people to catch a woman.
抓个女的带这么多人
I was indeed too careless
这件事情
for this matter,
确实是我大意了
but shouldn't Hua...
但是华
his elder brother
他哥哥难道就不该
give us an explanation?
给我们个说法吗
He came to Shanghai that day
他那天来上海
and clearly promised to discipline his...
明明保证过会管好他
I'm in the photo.
那张照片上有我
You know how much trouble it would be for me
你明知道那个记者跑了
if that journalist ran away.
对我会是多大的麻烦
Sir,
副局长
Hua Zhen was there.
对面是华桢
I couldn't do anything
他跟我过不去
when he wanted to block me.
我也很难办
He just had a cup of coffee,
他只是喝了杯咖啡
that's all, right?
不就这样吗
We all know he was pretending.
我们都知道他是在演戏
Where's the evidence?
证据呢
If you can give me
但凡你能拿出
even a shred of evidence,
一丝一毫的证据
I can call
我的电话
Hua Liang directly.
就已经打到华梁桌上了
But till now,
可是从头至尾
you only know Hua Zhen had a cup of coffee.
华桢他只是喝了杯咖啡
As for this matter,
这件事
we have to deal with it ourselves.
我们只能自行处理了
If Nakamura and Hua Liang know that,
让里见和华梁知道了
you and I are hard to explain.
你我都难堪
But sir,
可是副局长
will we just let it go?
这件事情就这么算了吗
If Hua Zhen
如果华桢
isn't Hua Liang's brother,
不是华梁他弟弟
it wouldn't have been so difficult at all.
这根本就没有这么难办
I just shot him
我一枪崩了他
and all problems are gone.
就什么事儿都没了
As I said before,
我说过
if Hua Liang can discipline
如果华梁能管好
his brother,
他的弟弟
this is his family affairs.
这就是他的家事
But if he can't,
如果管不好
then we have to
那么只能
discipline for him.
我们替他管了
Do you mean...?
您的意思
Do it your way.
就按你的意思去办吧
You have my back,
你的背后还有我
and Nakamura
我的背后
supports me.
不是还有里见吗
I understand.
我明白了
You just said
你刚刚说
Hua Zhen's cohorts are a man and a woman.
华桢的同伙是一男一女
It should be easy to find out
在上海
the man and woman who can contact
能跟他往来的一男一女
with him in Shanghai, right?
应该不难查吧
A man and a woman...
一男一女
It's easy.
不难查
Don't worry,
您放心
Mr. Feng.
冯科长
Where is Chen Hao?
陈浩呢
Today is Sunday,
今天是星期天
so all staff are on holiday,
都放假了
just the two of us on duty.
就我们俩值班
Did he come here yesterday?
他昨天来了吧
Yes, he did.
昨天来了
He stayed here the whole time yesterday?
昨天他一直都在刑警科
He went out with us
昨天中午的时候
at noon yesterday.
跟我们二组出去过
It was our turn
昨天是轮到我们
to go out for patrol.
出外勤巡逻
Did he ever leave alone
他巡逻的时候
on patrol?
自己单独离开过吗
We spread out during the patrol,
我们中途都分开过
one for a piece of area.
一人负责一片
And then I haven't seen him.
后来就没见过他了
Have you seen him with anyone
最近有看见过
from the Fourth Station recently?
他跟四所的人有来往吗
No, Sir.
这个 倒没见过
Give me the files
把四所的档案
of the Fourth Station.
给我拿过来
Yes, sir.
是
Good Morning.
早安
Good night.
晚安
I haven't locked my door yet.
我门还没反锁呢
What's up?
怎么了呀
Dongbao is in trouble.
冬宝他出事儿了
What's the matter?
出什么事儿了呀
He fainted at the dock.
他在码头晕倒了
How could it be?
怎么会晕倒
Does his wound relapse?
之前的伤复发了呀
I don't know.
我也不知道
Xiang Yuansheng and Erbai
向远生 二白
just sent him to the hospital.
刚给他送去医院
How could it be so serious?
怎么会这么严重呢
I don't know.
我说不清楚
Why don't you visit him yourself?
你自己去看不就知道了
You tell me first.
你先告诉我
I really can't say it clearly.
我真说不清楚
If you don't go,
你要是不去
you will regret.
你等着后悔吧
Let's go, Captain.
走吧 队长
Hongfa.
鸿发
The car is coming.
来了 来了
Get off.
下呀
Well, you've already arrived.
不是 你来都来了
Get off the car.
快下车呀
You said
你不是说
something happened to Dongbao, right?
冬宝出事儿了吗
Then why bring me to the Fourth Station?
带我来四所干吗
You'll know when you get in.
你进去你就知道了
Don't ask me.
你别管了
Hongfa.
鸿发
See, who's here?
你们看 谁来了
Captain.
队长
Dongbao, are you alright?
冬宝你没事儿吧
I'm all right, captain.
没 没事儿队长
That's great.
没事儿就好啊
Yu, long time no see.
小玉好久不见
How are you?
你还好吗
I'm good.
挺好的
See, I'm smart, right?
看吧 还是我厉害吧
I bring the Captain here,
给队长请来了
and you can't do this.
你们谁请也来不了
Yes, you're smart.
你厉害
You guys go ahead,
你们先忙
and I'll talk to Xiang Yuansheng.
我去跟向远生说个事儿
OK, hurry up.
行 那你
It's almost done.
快好了
If you sit down, we can eat.
坐下就能吃
OK.
好
Why are you here?
你怎么也来了
I know what you're worried about.
我知道你在担心什么
I'm also called over.
我也是被大家喊过来的
As for the incident yesterday,
昨天那件事情
Feng Guangyun will definitely investigate.
冯广云一定会查下去
It's too dangerous that
我们在这儿见面
we meet here.
太不安全了
I'm leaving now.
我准备先走了
Have you finished?
说完了
Come here and sit down.
过来坐吧
Ronghua,
左哥
I have something to do
我十六铺分局
at Shiliupu Police Station.
还有些事儿
Bye, enjoy the meal.
你们吃吧
Captain,
队长
well,
那个
please forget
我上次说的那些话
what I said last time.
你别往心里去啊
Don't you understand me?
我你还不了解吗
I said that without thinking seriously.
想起什么说什么
I didn't mean it.
我那 那都是气话
I've known you for so many years,
这么多年
so I definitely understand you,
我肯定了解你啊
It's okay, and I didn't take it in mind.
没事儿 我没往心里去
Today, I want to
今天借这个机会
take the opportunity
我想跟大家正好
to be honest with you.
坦白一下
I do want to have less contact
我确实想跟四所
with the Fourth Station.
少一些联系
Because I am still a policeman.
因为我还在做警察
Being a cop means trouble will find you.
做警察就会有麻烦事
You used to be a cop,
你们也都当过警察
so you must understand this.
应该能理解
Now you all
现在各自
have your own lives,
都有各自的生活了
and I don't want to
我不想因为我的麻烦
bring my troubles to you.
牵扯到大家
I hope you can understand.
希望你们能理解
Erbai, I'm leaving.
走了 二白
Where are you go?
哪儿去
Are we those who scare trouble?
我们是那怕麻烦的人吗
Who's afraid of trouble?
谁怕麻烦呀
We've never been afraid of trouble.
我们从来没怕过麻烦
Captain,
队长
We Fourth Station have finally come together.
我们四所好不容易聚齐
If you leave,
要是少你一个
it's not our Fourth Station.
就不叫四所了
I spent so much time bringing you here,
这费半天劲给你拉来
now you want to leave.
你又要走
Can you stay a little longer
你就多待一会儿
just once?
你就这一次行不行
That's enough.
行了
You brat,
臭小子
I've always said
我一直说
the Fourth Station
四所呢
is a big family.
就是一个大家庭
If you really regard it
你要真把这里当成自己
as one of your own homes,
曾经的一个家
just stay and gather with us.
就留下来聚聚
If you want to
至于以后
gather with us later, just come here.
你要是想聚 就过来
And if you don't,
不想聚
you just live your life,
你过你的
and we live our lives.
我们过我们的
Is it OK?
你看行吗
Enough,
行了
just follow the director today.
就听所长的吧 今天
I'll stand by your side and watch you
站在你旁边看着你
Yuansheng, stop working.
远生 别忙活了
Come on.
过来吧
You can't run away.
跑不了
Open the pot.
开锅
It smells good.
好香啊
The liquor has been poured.
酒都倒好了啊
Come.
来
Come here, Yu.
来小玉
Sit down, Erbai.
二白坐下坐下
Coming.
来
Rare occasion.
难得难得啊
Indeed a hard-won occasion.
这个 难得啊
Long time has passed since the last time
这么久了
all Fourth Station members gathered.
四所头一次聚得这么齐
The first toast
这第一杯酒
to Dongbao and Yu.
得敬给冬宝和小玉
Dongbao has big news to announce.
冬宝有重大消息要宣布
Why are you so happy?
乐什么呀
Say it.
说呀你
What's up?
什么呀
I tell you a happy event.
那我跟大家说个喜事儿
I'm going to be a father.
我要当爹了
Good news, isn't it?
是不是好消息
Yu.
小玉
you're going to be a mother.
你要当妈妈了
Let's have a toast.
这杯该不该喝
Cheers.
该 来来来
To Dongbao.
敬冬宝 来
Yu,
小玉
congratulations.
恭喜啊 恭喜
No wine for Yu.
小 小玉就别喝了
Drink some tea instead.
你喝茶就行
Glad to hear that.
好消息
When did you find it?
什么时候的事儿啊
Just recently.
就前两天才发现的
Captain,
还有队长
I got a job
我现在呢
at the dock.
在码头找了份差事
Yu used to watch over
之前小玉呢
and clean
不是帮人家看仓库
a warehouse.
打扫仓库吗
Now that she's pregnant,
然后她现在怀了孕了
I got a job
我就也在仓库
at the warehouse.
找了份差事
During the day, I work as a porter.
白天 我码头搬货
At night, I work as a warehouse keeper.
晚上 我看仓库
I can accompany her.
还能陪她
And I get paid twice.
我还能挣两份钱
So, you don't have to
所以你们就
worry about us.
别担心我俩了
We've talked about it.
我们商量好了
We are going to
我们要一起
open a breakfast shop.
开个早餐铺子
We will work hard
我们一定踏踏实实
and live a good life.
把日子过好
Great.
好
Don't worry about us.
你们就别担心了
Dongbao, good for you.
冬宝 好样的
Good man. Sit down.
好男人 坐下来
One more good news.
第二个
Welcome back,
来 欢迎
Xiang,
小向回来
and
更欢迎
Captain
陈浩队长
Chen Hao.
回归我们大家庭
Welcome back.
欢迎
Let's eat.
动筷
Can't wait.
来吧
Have some meat.
吃肉吃肉
The Fourth Station has a tradition.
按四所的这个老传统啊
At every
一逢到这个
festival,
重大节日是吧
everyone has to perform a show.
都要表演节目
Look,
大家看啊
someone
有些人
is fully prepared.
家伙什儿都准备好了
Showtime!
怎么样 来一个
The truth is
咱说好了
I didn't prepare it.
这不是我准备的啊
Every festival,
每次逢年过节
you take it out
你就拿这个
and ask me to give a performance.
让我表演节目
How festive today is!
今天好日子嘛
Give him a round of applause.
来一个 来 鼓掌鼓掌
Come on.
来一个
Alright, you win,
今天我给大家演一个
I'll give a performance.
没问题
But you will perform with me.
但你也别跑
Let's perform together.
咱俩一起
That's a "No".
没我事儿
Every festival,
每次逢年过节
you ask me to perform a show.
你都让我演一个
Director.
所长
Stop it.
瞎起哄你
Every festival, you ask me to perform.
逢年过节就让我演节目
I hate performing
最烦的就是逢年过节
at festivals.
演节目
Come on.
来啊
I'll help you in the show.
我给你架一个啊
What's the performance?
来
How
我来一个
about
给大家来一段
an impromptu rap.
即兴的一段小数来宝吧
Rap.
数来宝
Great.
好 好
Listen up.
开始了啊
Wonderful.
厉害啊厉害
Awesome.
好
Great.
厉害
♪White dew fell, autumn wind blew.♪
白露起送秋风
♪Xiang Yuansheng came from Nanjing.♪
打南京来了个向远生
It's you.
说你呢
♪Xiang Yuansheng.♪
这个向远生
What about him?
怎么着
♪He's tall and walks like a breeze.♪
身高八尺行如风
♪To join the Fourth Station,♪
为进四所
♪he competed with my brother.♪
跟我弟弟把岗位争
He still remembers it.
还记得这事儿呢
♪I didn't expect me♪
但是没想到
♪to underestimate him.♪
小瞧了这个公子哥
What happened?
怎么了
♪He's bold, careful, and skilled.♪
他胆大心细本领多
♪To catch the abductor,♪
为了抓住诱拐犯
♪he went to the French Concession.♪
到法租界里把案办
No one else dares to go there.
那地儿别人不敢去啊
♪The Captain made a plan.♪
是队长带队做方案
♪I actively cooperated with him.♪
我积极配合卯劲儿干
♪Hongfa was clever and diligent.♪
鸿发机灵不偷懒
♪Dongbao was positive and brave.♪
冬宝积极又勇敢
♪Minmin was careful and persevering.♪
这个珉敏心细有毅力
It's me.
说我呢说我呢
♪If it weren't for Yuansheng,♪
要不是远生
What?
怎么的
♪I would have introduced her to my cousin.♪
我肯定介绍给我表弟
It has nothing to do with your cousin.
跟你表弟有什么关系
You mentioned
不是 你说了半天
everyone.
挺热闹
What about me?
我呢
I'm talking about you now.
现在就说你 现在说你
♪And there's♪
还有咱
♪our nagging Director.♪
爱唠唠叨叨的咱所长
♪If I don't see him, I'll miss him.♪
这一天不见还有点儿想
He misses me.
想我
♪You brought everyone together.♪
是你把大家聚一起
♪We sincerely thank you.♪
我们衷心感谢你
♪Everyone from the Fourth Station is here.♪
今天四所一聚齐
♪May we♪
祝愿我们这些人
♪never be separated.♪
天长地久永远不分离
♪Bravo. Never be separated.♪
好 不分离
Please don't ask me
以后你别再
to perform again.
让我演节目了
Whose turn is it?
该谁了
Minmin, come on.
珉敏来一个
No.
我来不了
Your turn, Minmin.
来一个  来一个珉敏
If I sing,
那我唱了
you all have to applaud.
大家都得给我鼓掌
OK.
好
We'll applaud you.
没唱完也给你鼓掌
Come on.
来
♪What mirror do you look in this morning?♪
清早起来什么镜子照
♪What does your perfume smell like?♪
梳一个油头什么花香
♪What face cream do you put on?♪
脸上擦的是什么花粉
♪What lipstick♪
口点的胭脂
♪do you wear?♪
是什么花红
Fabulous.
好
Let's propose a toast
这 这杯酒
to Minmin, OK?
敬珉敏好不好
OK.
好 来
Such a brilliant show.
她真不错
She is an artist.
多才多艺啊
Xiang, now it's your turn.
小向小向你来一个
Forget it.
我 我来不了
Propose a toast.
来 让你提一个
Cheers.
敬一个
Come on.
来来来 一起来
Wait.
等 等会儿
What is the slogan of the Fourth Station?
四所的口号什么来着
Support justice.
匡扶正义
Protect the people.
保护百姓
Cheers.
干杯
Dream.
梦
That is.
那是
Our.
我们的
If.
如果
We.
我们
Meet.
相遇
See you, Ms. Shi.
石老师 再见
If.
如果
We.
我们
Meet.
遇见
Uvular consonant.
小舌音
Keep it in mind.
下次记住了
Pack up
收拾好东西
and go home.
赶紧回去吧
No mission today?
今天没有任务要说吗
Did you learn your French
你的法语
in a French class?
也是在法语班学的吗
I learned French when
是我在法国
I studied in France.
读书的时候学的
You've been to France?
你去过法国
My parents used to do business in Nanjing.
我父母以前在南京经商
Later, my family decided to move to Paris.
后来全家决定搬去巴黎
I lived in France for five years
我在法国生活了五年
and then returned to Nanjing alone.
然后一个人回到南京
Then, I went from Nanjing to Moscow,
又从南京去了莫斯科
then Shanghai.
最后才来的上海
What about your family?
那你的家人呢
They stayed in France.
他们留在法国了
I have two elder brothers
我还有两个哥哥
and a younger brother.
一个弟弟
What about you?
你呢
Did you grow up in Shanghai?
是在上海长大的吗
Me?
我
I grew up
我从小
by the sea in Fengxian.
在奉贤的海边长大
My parents are fishermen.
父母都是渔民
We lived in a little fishing town
住在奉贤海边的
by the sea in Fengxian.
小渔村
Later, I went to
后来考去了
the Zhejiang Police College.
浙江警察学校
Later, I came to Shanghai.
再后来来的上海
You've been fishing since you were a kid.
所以你从小就会捕鱼
You're asking a fisherman
你竟然问个渔民
if he can catch fish.
会不会捕鱼
I'll take you to the sea
有机会我带你去海边
to fish when possible.
捕鱼捞虾
I don't think it will ever happen.
应该不会有那样的机会
Why are you laughing?
你笑什么
Nothing.
没什么
I thought we had nothing to talk about
我以为我们除了工作
except work.
没有什么可聊的
It was good for us to have a chat.
还聊了几句 挺好
How could the power go out?
怎么会停电
Yeah.
对啊
There are frequent power outages here.
这里经常停电
Pack up and go home.
你快收拾好东西回去吧
Please show your ID.
请出示下证件
Mr. Feng,
冯科长
I know you.
我认得你
Last time,
之前来的时候
I made it clear to you.
不是说得很清楚了吗
The shipyard is off-limits.
造船所最近不让进
I have an important case.
我有重要的案子
Show him the search warrant.
搜查令
I've
之前
talked to someone
已经跟你们警卫处的人
from the Security Dept.
交涉过了
Give them a call.
你打个电话就知道了
Who was on duty
二十一号那天
on the 21st?
你们谁在这儿值班
Both of us.
我们两个都在
We're on duty this week.
这个星期都是我们值班
On the 21st, a patient checked in.
那天住进来一个病人
His name is Hua Zhen.
登记的名字叫华桢
He's from the S.M.C. Do you remember him?
电雷学校的 有印象吗
Speaking of the S.M.C,
你说电雷学校
I remembered.
我倒是有点印象
Was there
他那天
a girl
旁边是不是还跟了
with him?
一个年轻的女的
I thought
好像
there was a girl.
是有个女孩儿
Is that girl her?
是她吗
Yes.
是她
She was wearing a police cap.
她当时戴了一顶警帽
So I looked at her a few times.
我还多看了两眼
Mrs. Peng.
彭太太
He's awake.
他醒了
Ganwen,
甘文
here they are.
他们来了
Hello, Mr. Peng.
彭记者 你好
Thank you for saving my life.
三位的救命之恩
I'll never forget it as long as I live.
甘文没齿难忘
Lean back to save some effort.
您靠在后面 省点力气
Careful.
慢一点 慢一点
Give them the photos.
把照片拿给他们
Ganwen asked me
这些是甘文
to get these back.
让我取回来的
It contains
这里面装的
the reason why he's been arrested
有他被抓的原因
and the truth you wanted.
也有你们想知道的真相
Two months ago,
两个多月前
Shen Bao asked me to write a story.
《申报》让我写报道
So, I went to
我就去了一个叫
the Hongji Benevolent Society
弘济善堂的地方
to collect material.
收集素材
That was why
我每天和那些难民
I talked to refugees
在一起聊天
every day.
就因为这个
I happened to find out
我偶然发现那个地方
there were always ronins in that place.
总有一些浪人出入
So,
所以
I contacted the NSO
我联系救国会
and formally investigated
正式调查起了
the Japanese boss.
那个日本老板
This is a photo from the NSO.
这是救国会给我的照片
Is the Japanese boss
您说的那个日本老板
you are talking about
是这上面
Nakamura Naoki?
叫里见直树的人吗
Yes.
对
I secretly
这个照片
took this photo
就是我在酒楼里
in the restaurant.
偷偷拍下来的
Nakamura Naoki served in
这个里见直树
Division No. 4
曾经在关东军
of Kwantung Army.
第四课任职
He was in charge of propaganda.
负责军中宣传
I gave this photo
我把这张照片
to the NSO.
给了救国会
One day,
后来有一天
at the Shiliupu Wharf,
我在十六铺码头
I saw Nakamura Naoki
看到里见直树
get on a cargo ship
上了一艘
named Shinei Maru.
叫新荣丸号的货船
I got on the ship
我就混在搬运工里
among the porters.
也上了船
The pictures
你们手上
you have
看到的这些照片
were taken secretly by me on the ship.
就是我在船上偷拍到的
I inquired
而且我还在码头
at the wharf.
打听过了
The owner of the goods
这船货的主人
was Nakamura Naoki.
就是里见直树
The ship
而船
was bound for Nagasaki port.
是开往长崎港的
Are these photos of the cargo on board?
这些照片都是船上的货
Yes.
对
This is bristles.
这是猪鬃
This is tungsten sand.
这是钨砂
These are the ordnance
这些都是兵工部门
supplies to the army.
配给军队的东西
Do you know
你知道这些桶里
what was in these buckets?
是什么吗
It was tung oil.
是桐油
All of them are military supplies.
都是军需品
These things should be
这些本应该
in the warehouse of the Kuomintang army.
在国军仓库里的东西
How did they end up
怎么会在
on a cargo ship bound for Japan?
去往日本的货船上
The cargo boxes
货箱上面
were all covered with tea leaves.
都盖有一层茶叶
These items were covered below.
下面才是这些东西
I guess
我估计他们是想
they wanted to sell these goods to Japan
以茶叶的名目
with the disguise of tea.
把这些货物卖去日本
Are bristles and tung oil
猪鬃和桐油
also military supplies?
也是军需品
Yes.
对
Bristle brushes are used to
从军舰 飞机
paint warships, airplanes,
军用汽车的喷漆
and vehicles
到清刷机枪枪管
and to clean
大炮炮筒
the barrels of machine guns and cannons.
都能用到猪鬃刷
About tung oil,
而至于桐油
there is a common saying,
通俗的说法
a tung tree
一株桐树
is equivalent to a machine gun,
抵得过一顶机关枪
a tung nut
一个桐果
is equivalent to a grenade,
抵得过一颗手榴弹
and a tung seed
一粒桐籽
is equivalent to a bullet.
抵得过一发子弹
There is only one possibility
这些军需品
of selling these munitions to Japan,
整船整船地卖到日本
and that is smuggling.
只有可能是走私
You're right.
对
I only took this photo
我当时在酒楼
in the restaurant.
就只拍下来这一张照片
I thought
我当时就是觉得
they were trading something.
他们在交易什么
Now, it looks like
现在看来
they were trading
他们就是在合伙交易
this ship of munitions.
这船军需品
Mr. Peng,
彭记者
did you see the face of
这照片上只有背影的人
the man with only his back in the photo?
你见过他的正面吗
No.
没有
Mr. Peng,
彭记者
I have a question.
我想问
The people who tried to take you
那些要把你抓走的人
were trying to get
就是为了拿到
the pictures and the negatives,
这些照片跟底片
right?
对吗
Yes.
对
The more they feared,
他们越是惧怕
the more it showed
越是说明这件事情
that this was matters a lot.
非同小可
It's a pity
只可惜
that the ship
现在这艘船
should have arrived in Nagasaki.
应该已经开到长崎岛了
I have no evidence
而我手上除了这些照片
other than these photos
和我的推测
and speculation.
也没有其他什么证据了
What do we do
接下来
next?
我们准备怎么办
Mr. Peng needs time to recover.
彭记者还需要养伤
I will keep investigating
我会接替他继续查下去
until I find evidence of
直到查到
their smuggling.
他们走私的确凿证据
That's just his speculation.
彭记者刚才也是推测
Maybe
也许
the situation
最后的结果
is not what you think.
不是你想的那样
I've found the answer,
其实我心里有答案
so do you, I think.
你们应该也有了吧
I just don't know
只是不知道为什么
why I see
我心里还有
a glimmer of hope deep in my heart.
最后一丝希望